<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A lamentable complaint of the commonalty, by way of supplication to the high court of Parliament, for a learned ministery. In Anno. 1585</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21422</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7739</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111660</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846945</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846945</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11944</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21422)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11944)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 220:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A lamentable complaint of the commonalty, by way of supplication to the high court of Parliament, for a learned ministery. In Anno. 1585</title>
                  <author>Waldegrave, Robert, 1554-1604, attributed name. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[88] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Robert Waldegrave,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1585]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Robert Waldegrave--MiU.</note>
                  <note>Last leaf blank.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11944:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11944:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11944:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11944:2"/>
            <p>A LAMENTABLE COMPLAINT OF THE COMMONALTY, BY WAY OF SVPPLICATION TO THE HIGH COVRT OF PARLIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT, FOR A LEARNED MI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NISTERY.</p>
            <p>In Anno. 1585.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11944:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>BEcauſe our deſire was, that this our complaint ſhould be communicated to euery one of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable of parliament, and finding no other waies to perfourme the ſame: we deſired that it might be done by the way of printing. And we pray, that this our requeſt may be made knowne to her maieſty, who in all ciuill cauſes appertaining to this preſent life, is a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of mercy, ſo we truſt that her bowelles of pitty and compasſion will abound and exceede in this matter, that concerneth the ſaluation of the ſoules of her louing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, and that as ſhe is the head and cheefeſt, ſo wee truſt that her hand will be moſt forward in this ſacrifice and ſeruice of the lorde, which he requireth for all the benefites that he hath moſt plentifully powred vppon her maieſty, and vppon vs by her maiesties gratious gouernment.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11944:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE CRY AND COMPLAINT of the Commonalty of this Lande, by <hi>way of Supplication, to the right honourable aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> of the high court of parliament, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide by law a godly learned miniſtery.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N moſt humble maner that we may, (moſt gratious Soueraign, and right honorable aſſembly) we fall down before your feete, euen in the duſt, preſenting before you a moſt waighty petition. It is not much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like that petition, that HESTER made to the King ASSVERVS: ſaying,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſter.</hi> 7.4.</note> If I haue found fauour in thy ſight, and if it ſeeme good vnto the King, let my life bee giuen me at my petition, and my people at my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. For we are ſold, I and my people to be deſtroied, to bee ſlaine, and to periſh. And when the king demaunded, who had done that deede, the Queene aunſwered that wicked HAMMON. In like wiſe, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny congregations of vs, as be in this Land, deſtitute of a godly miniſter, to preach vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the word of Saluation (as there be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding many) do intreat for our life, and the life of our Neighbours. For we are ſold to be deſtroyed, to be ſlaine, and to periſh eternally, if by your gratious helpe, ſpeedy
<pb facs="tcp:11944:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>remedy be not had. If queſtion bee made, who hath done this deede? we aunſwere, the blinde guides, and vnlearned Curates, that are ſet ouer vs. In deede, we confeſſe, that our ſinnes, and the ſinnes of our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers are multiplied without meaſure, and grown exceeding great, and haue grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly prouoked the Lords wrath, to ſtrike vs with ſuch â grieuous plague as there is none greater vnder the heauens. As wee reade, that the Lorde threatned the Iewes by the Prophete ZACHARIE, ſaying: For, loe I will raiſe vp a Shepeheard in the Lande, which ſhall not looke for the thyng that is loſt, nor ſeeke the tender Lambes, nor heale that is hurt, nor feede that which ſtandeth, but hee ſhall eate the fleſh of the fat, and teare their claws in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. O Idoll ſhepheard that leaueth the flockel The like deſcription is made of will Shepheards, in the 34. of EZECHIEL, with â Woe pronounced againſt them. By this, we truſt it doth appeare, what we requeſt; euen, that it woulde pleaſe God, to mooue you, to make a firme, and ſtable law, like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lawes of the Medes and Perſians, that cannot be altered; nay, rather to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme God his lawe, already eſtabliſhed in
<pb facs="tcp:11944:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>his Worde, that euery Congregation of vs may haue one, or two Godly learned prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers ſet ouer vs, as euery Congregation is greater, or leſſer, and theſe dumb Idolls, the moſte peſtilent enimies wee haue in the worlde, remooued from vs as farre as the Eaſt is from the Weſt; And that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer doth violate that holy law and decree, let his body be drawne in peeces, and his houſe made â Iakes; becauſe he ſeeketh the diſhonor of the mighty God, the king of all the earth, as by NABVCHADNEZER it was decreed. So ſhal it appeare, that you are not only carefull for this preſent age, ſo to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide that we may bee taught the feare of God, but that our poſterity may know it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and the children which are yet vnborn, may ſtand vp &amp; declare it to their children, that they may ſet their hope in GOD, and not forget the works of the Lord, but keep his commaundements. We confeſſe that the greateſt part of vs are the fartheſt of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deſire, and not ſo much as once thinke hereof: the more we are to be pitied. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, ſith ſome of vs hath taſted the good word of God, and how gratious the Lord is to thoſe which know &amp; feare him, in tender loue, and compaſſion, to our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb facs="tcp:11944:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>finding no other way, we vncouer the tiles of your houſe of Parliament, &amp; let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe with cordes before you, to ſtirre vp your bowels of compaſſion towards them; as the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which had the palſey, was brought before our Sauior Chriſt. Concerning the miniſter appointed to the houſe of God by his worde, we find it written (moſt noble Queene, &amp; right Hon. aſſembly) in that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Booke which you haue deliuered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, as the true word of God, &amp; ſo, with al thankſgiuing, we receiue it: that he muſt be blameleſſe in life, free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a great number of vices (which S. PAVL to TIMOTHIE &amp; TI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVS reherſeth) &amp; garniſhed with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vertues; &amp; aboue all, he muſt be skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to teach the word of God, able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort by ſound doctrine, &amp; to conuince the aduerſary. Yea, he muſt be that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, that is perfectly enſtructed in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to euery good worke; not onely to teach ſound doctrine, &amp; confute errors; but alſo to reform maners &amp; inſtruct in the way of righteouſnes, to caſt downe the proud, to raiſe vp the humble, to comfort the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed; to encourage him that walketh in the right way, to reproue him that runneth out of the way: and finally, to declare to all
<pb facs="tcp:11944:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>men, as Princes, Magiſtrates, and all other inferiour perſons, of what calling ſoeuer they be, their generall and particular duties out of the word of God. And therefore he is worthily compared, in the Goſpell to the rich houſholder, which bringeth out of his treaſury, things old and new. He is the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour of the moſt high king vnto his people, to declare vnto them the whole counſell of God. Afterward he is mightily to deuide the Word of God to the people, as the onely foode of their ſoules, a diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of the ſecreats of God, a father to beget vs with the immortall ſeede of the worde, a mother to nouriſh vs vp in the ſame: a ſtarr or light, to cauſe the glorious Goſpell of Chriſt to ſhine vppon vs, to be an example to vs, of an holy conuerſation: a guide and an eye, to direct vs in the waye of eternall life, Salt, to ſeaſon vs with the fear of God: a builder, to make a Temple of his people, which are liuing ſtones, for God to dwell in for euer: a Warriour to caſt downe the proud imagination of man, as a ſtrong hold and to bring euery thought to the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Chriſt: a prophet, to ſpeake in ſuch ſort, as when the vnbeleeuers, and vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned come in before them, they are rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="tcp:11944:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>and iudged, and ſo the ſecretes of the heart are made manifeſt, by the true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce and faith. For the which, they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the gift of God, with all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, &amp; ſay plainly, that God is in them: â skilfull Shepheard to feede God his flock with his Worde. Neceſſary therefore, yea, more neceſſary then foode and cloathing, is the moſte ſacred office of preaching, an ordinary and moſt excellent means of our ſaluation: which eyther to neglect, or to ſeeke for other meanes without it, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine fayth in Chriſt, is to preiudicate the wiſedome of God, and to looke for ſome extraordinarye working, which were to tempt the higheſt, and procure his indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vpon vs. And to proue the neceſſity of preaching, the Apoſtle PETER affirmeth, that in the Epiſtles of S. PAVL, there are ſundry thinges harde to bee vnderſtoode, which they that are vnlearned &amp; vnſtable, peruert, as they doe all ſcriptures, vnto their owne deſtruction. We therefore ſtande in great neede of that man of God before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, to open the Scriptures, with the key of knowledge: not only to the enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tening of our vnderſtanding, and confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our memory, but alſo to the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb facs="tcp:11944:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>of our ſinfull life. The trueth wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the example of the Eunuch, treaſurer to CANDACES Queene of Ethiopia, doth manifeſtly approoue; who being brought vp no doubt, in better maner then we the common people of the countrey, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to read the holy ſcriptures, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the prophet ESAY, at what time PHI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIP the Euangeliſt demaunded, whether he vnderſtood what he red, anſwered di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, How can I, without I had a guide. If therefore this noble man aided with bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter helpes then the common ſort, made it an hard thing to vnderſtand the Prophet without an interpreter, how can we the ſimple ſilly people vnderſtand it. For reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy whereof, the Lord hauing a prouident care ouer his Church, hath giuen Paſtours and Doctors for the gathering together of the Saintes for the worke of the miniſterie, and for the edification of the body of Chriſt, till we meete altogether (in the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of faith, and knowledge of the ſonne of God) vnto â perfect man, &amp; vnto the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the age of the fulneſſe of Chriſt. Much more we find in holy Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the office of Miniſters, tendyng to ſhew the excellencie of their function, and
<pb facs="tcp:11944:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>the wonderfull skill and knowledge that is required at their handes. So that it doeth plainly appeare, that God had a ſpecial care to prouide an euident and plaine lawe, that no vnskilfull man ſhould be ſet ouer his flocke, becauſe he is ſo plentifull in decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their duetie almoſt euery where: ſo that whoſoeuer deſireth to be fit for ſuch an office, deſireth a worthy worke, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by good right appertaineth double honor, and of whom it may worthily be ſayd with admiration. How beautifull are the feete of them which bring glad tidings of peace, and bring glad tidings of good things.</p>
            <p>Hauing laid downe our petition, and deſcribed in ſome maner a faithful paſtour; we craue leaue to ſhew after what maner we deſire that this paſtour ſhould exerciſe that his office among vs ſimple people, to our better edification. Neither doe we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire this of our ſelues, but, directed by the worde of God; as it is written by S. PAVL to the Corinthians, ſaying: I could not ſpeake vnto you as ſpiritual men, but as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to carnall, euen as vnto babes in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. I gaue you milke to drinke, and not meate; for ye were not yet able to beare it, neither yet now are ye able; for ye are yet
<pb facs="tcp:11944:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>carnall. Much more may be ſaid to vs En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhmen, Ye are carnall, and therfore haue neede to be fedde with milke, and not with ſtrong meate. This milke we take to be, not onely a familiar kinde of Catechizing, in as ſhort and plaine termes as poſſible may be (which we greatly long after) whereby we are made fit to receiue a more full declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as when we haue learned our letters, we come to ſpelling; but alſo a plaine and familiar kinde of handling of ſome portion of ſcripture, by deliuering the doctrine as the text yeeldeth it naturally without any enforcement, which doctrine receiueth an edge by exhortation. Contrary to this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of S. PAVLE do they who either Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chize not at all, or els do it in ſuch exquiſite maner, that it is made rather ſtrong meate, then milke. Some other take but one word for their text, and afterward runne into the mountaines, that we cannot follow them; not knowing how they went vp, or how they will come downe: whereas, if they had taken a good portion of the text, and had naturally expounded, and pithily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the ſame; by occaſion of that large text, we ſhould haue remembred a good part of the ſermon long time after; &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:11944:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>all contradiction he that will doe vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good, muſt abaſe himſelfe as lowe as he can, to our capacitie, as S. PAVL in the place before alleaged, &amp; alſo in the 6. to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes doth teſtify, ſaying: I ſpeake after the maner of men, becauſe of the infirmitie of your fleſh. For we countreymen are well content, that they ſpare to ſpeake vnto vs in the Latine, Greeke, &amp; Hebrew tongues, which we vnderſtand not; or to bring forth their Poets, Philoſophers, or Schole-points taken from the liberall Artes, to approoue their matter they haue in handling, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we are not acquainted: For in theſe things many preach themſelues, and not Chriſt Ieſus, and ſtudy to leaue an admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; fame of their learning behind them, whereat they chiefly ſhoote, rather then a godly edification of the inner man, which is by faith in Chriſt Ieſus. But when by thoſe helpes before named, they haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to a fuller vnderſtanding of the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, let them (in God his name) in a plaine and ſimple declaration of the truth, with known wordes, ſetting apart the enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſpeach of man his wiſedome, &amp; flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing eloquence of thoſe Corinthian prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, deliuer vnto vs the ſubſtance of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb facs="tcp:11944:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>out of a pure heart, with reuerence as in the ſight of GOD. So ſhall they haue PAVL for an example to imitate, whome FESTVS ſuppoſed, that much learning had made him mad; yet writing to the learned Corinthians, he profeſſed to know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaue onely Ieſus Chriſt, and him crucified.</p>
            <p>To this plaineneſſe of teaching, there ought to be ioyned a continuaunce in the holy exerciſe of the word, as S. PAVL ſaith to TIMOTHIE: Take heed to thy ſelfe, and to doctrine, and continue therein. And in an other place: Preach the worde, be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon. And for that cauſe, one chiefe propertie of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter is, to be vigilant ouer the flock, which though he carefully performe, yet in many yeeres, we come but to a ſmall meaſure of knowledge, and reformation of life. And no maruell, ſith the Apoſtles of Chriſt, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their maſter preach ſo often, and ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly, by the ſpace of three yeeres and more, yet for all his paines and trauaile in that time, they knew not well the vertue of his death and reſurrection. Yea, we heare ſay, that many painefull preachers both in townes &amp; cities, exerciſing the word three
<pb facs="tcp:11944:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>or foure times a weeke, yet doe they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of the ſmall profiting of the flocke. Then were it requiſit, that double dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce were vſed amongſt vs the rude people of the land, whoſe ignorance and dulneſſe to learne, as alſo ſtubburnneſſe to obey, are ſo great, that they are only known vnto God, to our ſelues, and thoſe fewe that haue had familiar conference with vs. And in trueth to ſpeake plainly, we are children in vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and men in malice, and all rude behauiour. For why ſhould we conceale from you the right honourable aſſembly of Parliament, the grieuouſneſſe of our mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, vnto whom we flie as vnto our parents, who onely haue power, next vnder God, to prouide a falue for our ſore? Yea, it grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs that we haue ſo long tyme concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the miſerable eſtate wherein we ſtand, from them who if they had known it to be ſo great, as we do feele it, would ere now haue prouided a remedy to redreſſe it. But touching theſe men, whome we ſo greatlye deſire to haue, in our ſimple iudgement, we thinke it not fit, that any man (were he neuer ſo wiſe &amp; godly) ſhould make choiſe alone of that man, that is to take a greater and more precious charge vpon him, then
<pb facs="tcp:11944:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>they that haue the moſt coſtly Iewells and treaſures of Princes, committed to their keeping. How requiſite were it, that ſuch â man as ſhould haue the bringing vp &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the ſonnes and daughters of the glorious king of heauen, (who loued them ſo dearely, that he ſpared not his one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten ſonne, to redeeme them with his moſt precious bloud) ſhould rather come into â publike place of trial, as it were into an ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Theater, that after publike prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and faſting, he might be ſeene &amp; viewed of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that if the beholders had as many eies as thei faine that Argos had, they ſhuld vſe them all, to ſift &amp; try out that man, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he were fit both in reſpect of his wiſedome &amp; vnderſtanding of the holy ſcriptures, as honeſty of life &amp; conuerſation, to take that noble charge vpon him. Moreouer, ſeeing we know that there be many ſubtile wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, tranſforming the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues into Angels of light, who ſeeke craftily to creepe in to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour the flocke: is it not to be feared, that they will more eaſily ſlide in through the hands of one then of many? Yea ſurely, the counſel &amp; aduiſe of mo then one for trial, is thought needful to be vſed in matters of les importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. As whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any man taketh on him
<pb facs="tcp:11944:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>the profeſſion of Phiſike (whoſe care is onely to ſee to the good eſtate of the body) notwithſtanding,
<note place="margin">11. of Henry the eight, cap. 3.</note> that he hath ſpent many yeeres both in the ſtudy of the liberal Arts, as in the ſecrets of Phiſike; yet is he to paſſe the hands of 4. approoued Doctors of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſike to be tried, whither he hath profited ſo much in the ſtudy of Phiſike, as is requiſite for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that profeſſion, leaſt, if he ſhould raſhly take vpon him to intermeddle in that Science, without ſufficient knowledge in the ſame, the bodily health of man ſhould ſuſtaine either damage or danger. Shal then the ſpirituall Phiſition that taketh vpon him to cure the maladies of the minde, (which are mo in number, more ſecret, and more difficult to be cured, and more dangerous if they bee cured) come leſſe furniſhed in the knowledge of his profeſſion then the other? And is it not requiſite, for the triall of his knowledge, that the number of skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full examiners and their diligence, ſhould be multiplied and increaſed ſo much the more as the ſoule doeth excell the body? Therefore ſeeing we are ſo prouident, that we can eſpy the euils that happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by vnskilfull Phiſitions, and by good meanes preuent them: why can we not ſee
<pb facs="tcp:11944:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>the palpable miſchiefs that we ſuffer in our ſoules by vnlearned Curates, and by many skilfull &amp; vigilant eyes exclude them? And this election many we finde to bee agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the ſcriptures; as we reade in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of MATHIAS, Acts. 1. of the Deacons Acts 6. Where the apoſtles and the church were aſſembled together about that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and of the election of the elders in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery church. Actes 14. PAVLE and BARNA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BAS, and IOHN, MARK with the Church were aſſembled together with faſting and prayer. Likewiſe, Act 16. where it ſeemeth that PAVL choſe TIMOTHIE alone, (when they of Lyſtra and Iconium preſented) yet in the firſt epiſtle of S. PAVLE wrote vnto TIMOTHIE, mention is made, that hee had impoſition of ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds by the Elderſhip, which conſiſteth of many. It appeareth alſo in the ſame epiſtle, that there were many in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of the church-officers at Epheſus: becauſe S. PAVL exhorteth TIMOTHIE, not to bee partaker of the ſinnes of others, that were fellow-chooſers with him, by yeelding, his conſent to the election of any vnworthy officer, but to keep himſelf pure, by denying his conſent, and hindring the election, as much as hee might, which no
<pb facs="tcp:11944:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>doubt is the true ſence of that place. The ſame is prooued, by the epiſtle to TITVS, where PAVL requireth him to ordaine el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in euery city, as he had apointed him: by the which ſaying: TITVS is reſtrained to that order or election, which S. PAVLE had appointed him, and it is to be thought that S. PAVL woulde appoint no other order to be obſerued, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he himſelf had vſed act. 14 and in the election of TIMOTHIE, which was practiſed by the apoſtles, act. 6. At the leaſte if it were but to keepe vniformitye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them. And vndoubtedly, if the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the word had their calling by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good and godly men, indued with gifts ſufficient for the triall of their doctrine and manners, then wee ſhould accept them as the angels of God, euen as Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe, then durſt no ſuch hedge-prieſtes, and caterpillers, as are ſpread ouer the land in great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, once thinke to haue any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the church of God to kill ſoules any more: when they ſhold vnderſtand that there were many vigilant watchmen apoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to keep the dore againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold not they that can thriue in no trade of life, ſuch men as Iob calleth the children of fools, &amp; the ſons of villains, which are more
<pb facs="tcp:11944:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>vile then the earthe, haue theire vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte refuge, and reſting place in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery. But if any man that is without natural affection to vs his poore brethren, ſhoulde giue ſome allowaunce to theſe vnpreaching miniſters, which wee haue: willing vs to contente oure ſelues with them, as our lawfull paſtours. In calling to our remembraunce theſe dumb idolles which oppreſſe vs, they renewe oure former griefe, and make our hearts euen bleede to thinke vpoon them. For who are appoynted to murther God his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but they? Howe farre are they vnlike theſe miniſters whome before we haue deſcribed? euen as muche as the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is to light. For if the worde of God bee the rule of righteouſneſſe, as it is in deede, and theſe men of whome we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, are not ſquared thereby; Howe can they auouche that they bee ſent of God? If not of him, you knowe of whome. For if Chriſte had ſente them, as his Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours, then, no doubt he would haue put his Embaſſage in their mouthes. Or if hee would haue had them occupiers of the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of preaching the word, wold he not firſt
<pb facs="tcp:11944:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>haue giuen it them? For how can the iudge of all the world cal men to accounts for the abuſe of that they neuer had? Nay rather; he ſaith to all the Paſtours of his flocke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſend them, as he did to EZECHIEL. Eate that thou findeſt, Eate this booke and goe, and ſpeake to the houſe of Iſrael. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do we finde in God his booke which you haue deliuered vnto vs, any other mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the word, except thoſe which are called blind guides, ſtarres without light, vnſauory ſalt, good for nothing, no, not for the dunghill, cloudes without water, idoll ſhepheards whom the Lord hath curſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from mount Ebal.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 3.6, 7.</note> And certainly when the biſhops went about to lay their handes vpon them, and vnwarily ſayd vnto them, ye haue clothing, let this ruine bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your handes: they ſhould haue ſaid, yea, rather ſworne on that day to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend fathers, ſaying, we can bee no hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, there is neither bread in our houſes, nor clothing, therefore make vs no gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the people. Or they might haue ſaid euery one of them, as we read in the Prophet ZACHARIE:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ach.</hi> 13.5.</note> I am no Prophet, I am an husbandman, for man taught me to be an heardman from my youth vp. O
<pb facs="tcp:11944:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>that they had ben ſo wiſe, ſo to haue done: But, if they themſelues will plead for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of their miniſterie, and ſhew forth themſelues as though they were workmen that need not to be aſhamed, Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proue it by their worke as S. PAVL doth prooue his Apoſtleſhip to the Corinthians, which was then called into queſtion by the falſe Apoſtles moſt vnworthily; as we doe call their miniſterie into queſtion moſt worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. He brought not forth vnto them his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters commendatorie from ſome great man; as peraduenture they will ſhew the letters of their Orders: but he willed them to call to remembrance their conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Chriſt, and the graces giuen them by his miniſtery in the Goſpel, and that was his epiſtle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatorie, and the ſeale of his Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to be red of all men. What thoſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were, it is plaine in the 1. Cor. 1. In all things ye are made rich in him, in all vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and all knowledge; ſo that you are not deſtitute of any gift, waiting for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. So wee pray you to try theſe men, their congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which in ſome places are more then two thouſand ſoules, and ſee their worke: mooue but theſe ſmal queſtions to try their
<pb facs="tcp:11944:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>knowledge, and you ſhall haue the like an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers for the moſt part. Honeſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are you â ſinner? Yea, the beſt of vs all are ſinners. Haue you ſinned in the 1. com. Thou ſhalt haue none other gods but me? I tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke God my whole truſt is in him. Haue you broken the 3. com. by taking Gods name in vaine? I ſweare as litle as any man, I thank God. Do you not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit adultery, or ſteale? No, God forbid, I perceue we ſhal find you no ſinner at length. But what is the puniſhment due for ſinne? As it pleaſeth God. Then God hath not alredy determined of that matter. So it may be. But how ſhall you be ſaued from your ſinnes, tel me that? By my good works, &amp; deeds I hope, &amp; ſom better lerned wil ſay, God is merciful. Through whom is God merciful vnto you? I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not tel that, for I am not learned. Then I will tel you, God is mercifull through Chriſt. But what was Chriſt? A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I trow. And was he no more? Yes, he was more. What more? I told you that I am not learned to anſwer ſuch deepe queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, I was neuer asked the like before. Are you not fully perſwaded that you ſhall go to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? No, for you cannot be certain of that your ſelf, but I hope wel, &amp; mean as wel as the beſt of you ſcripture me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Behold
<pb facs="tcp:11944:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>the nakednes of our ſoules, haue pity vpon vs, &amp; help vs to couer our ſhame. But al this time while you reaſon with vs of theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, we thinke our ſelues in a wildernes, or as a fiſh out of the water, &amp; ſo glad as may be to be rid of your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany. And ſome will not anſwer at all, but ſhake you of as buſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodies, in great anger, willing you to ſee to your own ſoules, &amp; let theirs alone. So that not aboue 2. or 3. of 100. (we ſuppoſe) of vs country people thorowout the land where theſe blind guides be, can make any better anſwer to the purpoſe, whereby you may probably co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iecture that the ſeed of eternal life is ſowen in our hearts. And the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe few is not wroght by any thing done by theſe ſilly miniſters; but rather the prouidence of God hath drawn vs into ſome other place by occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our calling, where we haue heard the word preched: or it may be, that God doth bleſſe ſome mens bare reading or hearing the ſcripture red, or confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with godly men, by the working of his ſpirit, where al other means faile the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But if queſtion be further made of the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of mortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the old ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the new man, of the benefits of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, of patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp;c. wherof the Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb facs="tcp:11944:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>were not deſtitute by PAVLES miniſtery; we thinke we heare men ſpeake parables, if mention be made of the comming of our Lorde Ieſus, then we tremble. But many of vs, can ſay the beleefe, the Lorde his prayer, and the tenne commaundementes; and yet God knoweth, without vnderſtanding or feeling. Neuertheleſſe, we think our ſelues to be in as good caſe, touching our ſoules health, as the beſt of you all. This is that great perfection whereunto our idol-mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters haue brought vs. Behold theſe labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, that neede not to be aſhamed of their worke? Read theſe their Epiſtles to their high commendation. But by this, that we haue ſayd, we think it to be playn ynough, that theſe men entred not in at the doore into the ſheepe-folde, but climed vp ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, and therefore, by the verdict of our ſauiour Chriſt, they are theeues and robbers, whoſe comming tendeth only to ſteale, to kil, and to deſtroy. Firſt, what good can come vnto vs by them, whome the Lorde hath not ſent, and ſanctified to the work of the miniſtery? what good can they do to the building of God his temple, that bring with them no tooles to worke with, but occupy the roome of a Figge tree that
<pb facs="tcp:11944:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>bear no fruit. Secondly, they which do not gather with Chriſt, according to his owne teſtimony, doe ſcatter: but it is manifeſtly known, that theſe men are no gatherers, but to ſathan. Therfore it is euident, that they do vs much harm, but no good at al. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how can thoſe be profitable vnto vs, and not rather an intollerable burthen, whom the Lord in his great diſpleaſure hath cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and laden with many woes, as in IERE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MIE 23. Woe be vnto the paſtours that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy and ſcatter the ſheepe of my paſture, ſaith the Lord: and after promiſing to ſet ſhepheards ouer them, that ſhould feede them. He ſheweth euidently that they ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and deſtroy, who feed not the people with the wholſom word of life. The like we read in the prophet EZECHIEL cap. 34. where it is written, after this manner. Thus ſaith the Lord God vnto the ſhepheardes. Wo be vnto the ſhepheards of Iſrael, that feede themſelues: ſhold not the ſhepherds feed their flocks? Ye eat the fat &amp; cloath ye with the wool, ye kill them that are fed; but ye feede not the ſheepe: the weak haue ye not ſtrengthned, the ſick haue ye not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, neyther haue ye bound vp the broken, nor brought againe that which was driuen
<pb facs="tcp:11944:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>away, neither haue ye ſought that which was loſt, but with cruelty and rigour, haue ye ruled ouer them, and they were ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red without a ſheapherd, and when they were ſcattered, they were deuoured of all the beaſtes of the feelde &amp;c. How can the ſheepe bee in worſe caſe then to bee in the hands of ſuch ſhepheards as regard them not, but ſcatter them to be deuoured of all the beaſts of the feelde? In the which ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall poueriſhments the wrath of the Lord doth not ſtay it ſelf, but his arm is ſtretched out ſtil to afflict the people of that kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e wher ſuch euil ſhepherds be, with al maner of bodily plagues alſo, as war and captiuity, whereof we read, in the Prophet ESAIAS, wher the Lord prouoketh forraigne natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to inuade the land of IVDEA, ſaying: All ye beaſts of the feeld come to, &amp; deuour euen all the beaſtes of the Foreſt &amp;c. The reaſon followeth. Their watchmen are all blinde, they haue no knowledge, they are all dumbe Dogges, they cannot barke, they lye, and ſleepe, and delighte in ſleeping. Laſt of all heereby it appeareth that wee are worſe by theſe Sheapheards, then if we had none, becauſe their skill ſeruing them onely to teache vs to ſay by heart, the
<pb facs="tcp:11944:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lord his prayer, the beleefe, and ten com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and peraduenture ſome part of the Cathechiſme: Which we know full little what they meane, and to reade the ſcripture vnto vs, which we heare as a ſtory that concerned the people of old time, with out any further applicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof vnto our ſelues: yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding by this, we think our ſelues to be in as good caſe, and as farre forward in the way of ſaluation as the beſt of them all, that haue continually heard the goſpel preached for the ſpace of theſe 26. yeares. This is the pollicy of Sathan, with the ſhewe of nothing, to make vs beleeue, that we haue al things, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to make vs think we are ful. This is that chainſhot, wherewith he ſlaieth thouſands vpon thouſandes, &amp; as it were, the iawbone of an aſſe; wherwith he doth make heaps v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon heapes, as we read of SAMPSON, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, if we had none at all, very ſhame would compell vs, to go to the places, where prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers are, and by the grace of God, wee ſhoulde heare them, euen the ſecreates of our harts diſcouered and condemned, and the only means to be ſaued, to embrace our ſauiour Chriſt by faith. By whoſe helpe we ſhold take ſuch taſte of the worde of God,
<pb facs="tcp:11944:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>that we ſhould afterward neuer be in reſt and peace before we had procured a good paſtour to be placed ouer vs. So ſhould not Sathan deceiue vs any more to cauſe vs to ſtay vpon theſe ſilly ſhepeheards, as vpon a broken ſtaffe of reede, vpon the which if a man leane, it will go into his hand &amp; pierce it. But if further reply be made of thoſe that tender our ſaluation but a litle, ſaying, you are ſufficiently prouided of preachyng by your quarterly ſermons. We anſwere, that 4. ſermons in the yere are as inſufficient or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily to make vs perfect men in Chriſt Ieſus, (to which end Paſtours and Doctors are giuen vs) as 4. ſtrokes with an axe are vnable to fell downe a mighty oke, or 4. ſhowers of raine of one houres continua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to moiſten the hard dry earth, and to make it fruitfull all the yeere long. Yea, our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren will as ſoone learne the Latin tongue by going to ſchoole 4. houres in a yeere, as we that be children in vnderſtanding the ſcripture, ſhall attaine to a true knowledge and reformation of life fit for a Chriſtian man, by hearing 4. ſermons yeerely: by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that the one is agreeable to nature, the other quite contrary. What if theſe men which preach theſe quarterly ſermons, be
<pb facs="tcp:11944:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>be the Paſtours of an other flocke? How can we with a good conſcience take thoſe ſermons from that flocke to which they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, and depriue them of that which by good right doth appertaine to them? That congregation which ſoweth vnto their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour all his earthly things, will be lothe to be defrauded of the vſe of any of his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual things; eſpecially, on the Saboth day. And ſurely, if this iniury were offered in matters concerning this life, it would in no maner wiſe be put vp and digeſted amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs. But admit it were lawful for the paſtors to borow ſo much time of their flocke as to preach theſe quarterly ſermons, yet if we conſider the ſmal profiting of the Apoſtles of Chriſt in a long time, who were often taught and after the beſt maner, by their maſter, and the incredible dulnes &amp; backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes of vs countrey people, that are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into the laſt and worſt age; and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding great inequalitie of our teachers in compariſon of our Sauiour Cſtriſt: it may eaſily moue you to thinke, that 4. ſermons were farr to litle, and that 400. rather were more requiſit (if it were poſſible thei could be attained vnto) to bring vs to the vnitie of faith, &amp; acknowledging of the ſonne of
<pb facs="tcp:11944:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>God, which is the end of the miniſtery, as S. PAVL writeth to the Epheſians. But ſeing we haue the expreſſe wordes of the ſame ſame Apoſtle to TIMOTHIE, willing him, &amp; in him al paſtours to preach the word, &amp; to be inſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, &amp; to continue therein; as alſo the example of himſelf, which he recommended to the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Epheſus, &amp; conſequently to all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors to be imitated, ſaying: Watch there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp; remember that by the ſpace of three yeeres, I warned euery man night and day with teares; this controuerſie may ſoone be ended, yea the wofull experience almoſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where, which is the ſchoolemaſter of fooles, doth make open proclamation, that theſe 4. ſermons are to ſlender a diet for vs. But if it were graunted (will ſome ſay) that it is fit, yea neceſſary, that euery congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould haue a painfull preacher or two, if it be greater; which we take to be as clere as the light, and denied of none but of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Athiſts: yet were it pity (ſay they) to diſplace theſe vnlearned Curates, and to turne them &amp; their family forth a begging. But were it not a greater pity by farre, to ſee theſe blind guides the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to fall into the pit of hel, &amp; â multitude of ſouls in the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,
<pb facs="tcp:11944:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>that are almoſt innumerable to follow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there to ſtarue &amp; pine away eternally, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing depriued of all foode that ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them? Nay, ſeing they did neuer ſweat for the place which they haue inuaded, nor entred in by the dore, but climed vp ſome other way by euil means, &amp; no good faith; &amp; being entred, haue made hauocke of the Lord his flocke, &amp; therefore moſt worthily are called thieues &amp; robbers, by the mekeſt man that euer was: they may thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues very mercifully delt withal, that they may quietly depart away with bag &amp; bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, and returne to their old occupations againe, from whence they came, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further puniſhment. But becauſe it may be thought that they haue committed this ſinne ignorauntly, and that vnder the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of lawe, and ſeeing that Chriſtian cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie doth extend it ſelfe very farre, we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that ſome litle penſion might very wel be deducted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the liuing of the BB. of the See where they were ordred &amp; be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: &amp; if that pention would not ſerue for their maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, the reſt might be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied either by their old occupations, or by exerciſing ſom inferior office in the church, and teaching of children. So by this ſparer
<pb facs="tcp:11944:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>diet, then heretofore they haue vſed, and the hearing of the Goſpell preached dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently by a learned man, which had bin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore precious vnto them becauſe they had no manifeſt viſion; as it fel out in the dayes of ELIAS, as we read in SAMVEL, they may be brought to bewayle the bloud (whereof they are guilty) of ſo many ſouls, as haue periſhed in their manifold ſinnes and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce, within their pariſhes, by reaſon they haue not giuen warning from God, out of his word, as he requireth in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet EZECHIEL; that if it be poſſible one way, or other, God his wrath might be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified in true humbling of themſelues; with many teares before the throan of grace, and they waſhed clean from the bloude of all men, by the rich mercies of God in Chriſt Ieſus. Were not this a better way by a thou ſand degrees; for theſe men them ſelues, though no regard were had of vs, then to ſuffer them ſtill to ad bloud vnto blod, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſuch time as the Lord his wrath were ſo kindled againſt them, that nothing but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain deſtruction, were to be looked to fall vpon them from the Lord, as we read of the wicked ſonnes of ELIE? Let them ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore depart, &amp; giue place to learned prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,
<pb facs="tcp:11944:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>if ſome ſacrilegious patrones will ſo permit; for we haue heard, that it hath bin preached at Paules croſſe, that in the two Vniuerſities of Cambridge and Oxford, there are mo then 300. able men fit for the miniſtery, beſide many other in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey that cannot enter into any church, or take any charge abroad, except in the firſt ſtep they enter in, they wil commit both ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and periury. How ſhal ſathan be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered by ſuch men, as in the firſt conflict haue receiued by him ſuch deadly wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds? For euen our plough boyes know it to be a common practiſe almoſt euery where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt patrons, that either they take a great ſumme of mony, or mony worth, as it were a fine, with ſuch ſleighty conueiance, as if they were iuglers, that no man ſhal eſpy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or any law preuent them, or make ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the tithes and glebeland, as it were a rent, &amp; many times all theſe practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be vſed togither, whoſe rauenous teeth, and alſo the paiment of the firſt fruites and tenthes, which the charge of their lawfull family, which the papiſts neuer knew, and alſo their tithes not paid them in ſo large a ſiſe as heretofore hath bene done, hath brought the churchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto ſuch an ebbe,
<pb facs="tcp:11944:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>that after their death their executours doe not bleſſe them, except it be certaine of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which haue ſundry benefices. The conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration wherof, hath abaſhed many of vs ſo much, that we haue ſmall regard to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain our children in learning, in hope of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny honeſt preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that way. Yea, we feare â further miſchiefe to fall vpon vs by theſe deuourers of holy things, of the which we hope there is none among you: for we ſee them euery day more diligent to compaſſe ſea and land, to find out IEROBOAM prieſts for vs (for they are the men that wil be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to part Chriſt his coat betwene them) and when they haue found them out, they make them two fold more, the children of the diuell, then themſelues; by cauſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a litle lucre ſake, to betray mens ſoules to the diuell. So that what by theſe cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant patrones, and IEROBOAM his prieſtes, ſinne and iniquitie is riſen ſo high, that it is now full ſea: Ignoraunce, blaſphemy, and contempt of the Saboth day doth raign in towne and citie: In pride &amp; vanitie, Sathan hath waſted his fruitfull wittes, that he can do no more. In theſe dayes all are become princes and nobles. The tire of women is lighter now, then of the ſtewes heretofore:
<pb facs="tcp:11944:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo that, if the people of the former tymes ſhould riſe out of their graues, and behold this preſent age, they would ſurely thinke that proude ſtraungers had inuaded and conquered this land. Quarels and ſtrifes in lawe are infinite. Whoredome is made but a ſport. Craft and deceit is euery wher practiſed. Vſury hath made as much frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip betweene man and man, as was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene CAINE and ABEL. No towne is emptye of the couetous which ioyne houſe to houſe, and land to land, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the poore is multiplied in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. But as concernyng many patrones; the leproſie of ſpoiling of the church, hath ſo pierced their bones and marow ſo deep, that it cannot be waſhed away, with any good law, be it neuer ſo wiſely made: For the Lawyers themſelues confeſſe, that by the helpe of Sathan, ſome men are as cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, to ouerthrowe the meanyng of good lawes, as it were to vndoe PENELOPE her webbe, as other are prouident by the good lawes to preuent miſchiefe. And therefore, the onely way and remedy to cure this cancker, is; to reſtore the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations to the Church, to whome by good right they doe belong. Which thing
<pb facs="tcp:11944:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>as it is moſt vndoubted by the worde of God, ſo alſo we heare that the learned are able to prooue it by the ciuill law: wherein it is ſaid, that a priuiledge is fruſtrate and of none effect, when it is abuſed, and that the people and other that had intereſt to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, aſſigned their right to the patrones, when they endued the church with landes and other prefermentes, it is plaine: who perſwaded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues that the patron would be careful inough to prouide a worthy ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who would not ſpare his lands and liuing to maintain him. But now the patrons nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther endow the church but ſpoile it, neither are they careful to prouide godly preachers but on the contrary, they labour tooth and naile to bring the caterpillers of Egypt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. And therefore what right can they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to claime any priuiledge? Which ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the godly wil not contend for, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhall ſee that reſtitution thereof tendeth to the glory of God, and the building of his church. Wil ye heare what the papiſts mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; yea they ſpeake it plainly that we main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine our hereſies (as they terme them) for aduantage, &amp; not for conſcience; affirming, that thei cannot be perſwaded, that we our ſelues are certified of the trueth of our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb facs="tcp:11944:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>or receiue any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort therby: for then (ſay they) would ye cheriſh and maintaine the profeſſors as we do, &amp; not vſe them as ſponges and ſpoile them as ye do. O lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table eſtate of the church! ô pitiful ſight to ſee her thus lie in the duſt. Come Ieremy, &amp; fill thy head with teares, as with a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, ceaſe neither day nor night, but make lamentation for the ſlaine of the daughter of Sion! Let thine eies caſt out riuers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the deſtruction of God his people! ô that ſome Angel of the Lord would come vnto you, as it wer from Gilgal to Bochim, and record in your eares the mercies of our God, in deliuering you from the captiuitie of Antichriſt, as it were from Pharaoh, and in giuing you â fruitful and peaceable land, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord ſaid by his goſpell which he deliuered vnto you: I wil neuer breake my couenant with you. You alſo ſhal make no couenant with the papiſts, the idolaters of this land, or any kinde of their vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but deſtroy al their idolatry and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition whatſoeuer. But ye haue not obeied my voyce in retaining idoll miniſters, by whom Sathan doth hold his kingdom faſt. Wherefore haue ye done this? At the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of which words, reproouing the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites
<pb facs="tcp:11944:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>for making a couenant with the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the land, all the people of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael lift vp their voices &amp; wept. Of the which weepyng, the place tooke his name Bochim, which in them was a true ſigne of earneſt repentance. And further, to aſſure them of God his mercies touchyng this fault, as alſo to binde themſelues more ſtraightly to the reformation thereof, they ſacrificed there vnto the Lord. The father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, of his rich &amp; abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant mercy, graunt, that in hearing the like ſinne; in ſuffring this idoll miniſtery amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs, you may draw out of your heds buckets of water of repentance, &amp; ioine your ſelues with them in the like reformation. But let ESDRAS come in alſo amongſt you, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile a greater matter then vnlawfull mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages. Let him rent his clothes and teare his garments, and pluck of the haire of his hed, and beard, and ſit downe aſtoniſhed, and let all be aſſembled vnto him that feare the words of the God of Iſrael, becauſe of the tranſgreſſions of this land. Let them fall downe vpon their knees &amp; ſpread out their handes vnto the Lord God, and ſay: ô my God, I am confounded and aſhamed to lift vp mine eyes vnto thee my God, for our
<pb facs="tcp:11944:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>iniquities are increaſed ouer our head, and our treſpaſſes are growen vp vnto the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens: from the dayes of our fathers haue we bene in great treſpaſſe vnto this day. And now, for a litle ſpace in the raigne of our ſoueraign Lady ELIZABETH, grace hath bin ſhewed from the Lord our God, in cauſing a remnaunt to eſcape, in giuing vs a naile in his holy place, that our GOD might lighten our eyes, and giue vs a litle reuiuing in our ſeruitude Papiſticall: For we were bondmen in Queene MARY her dayes; yet our God hath not forſaken vs in our bondage, but hath enclined mercy vnto vs in the ſight of Ieſus Chriſt, to giue vs life, and to erect the houſe of our God, and to giue vs a wall and defence in this land. And now our GOD, what ſhall we ſay? for we haue forſaken thy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes which thou haſt commaunded by thy ſeruaunts the Prophets and Apoſtles, ſaying: The land whether ye goe to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe, is an vncleane land, full of idolaters, and idoll miniſters: Now therefore ſhall ye erect in GOD his houſe, an holy mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, that ye may bee ſtrong and eate the goodneſſe of the land, and ſo to leaue it for an inheritaunce to your ſonnes for
<pb facs="tcp:11944:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>euer. And though thou diddeſt puniſh vs greeuouſly in Queene MARIE her days, and now in our days, by ſtirring vp the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes to diſturbe the peace of the lande, for the neglect of this holye ordinance, yet haſte thou puniſhed vs leſſe, then our ſinnes haue deſerued. Should we ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, to breake thy commandementes and permit this idoll miniſterye to remaine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs? a people of much abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, whereby ſinne doth flowe, as a riuer, in the land: wouldeſt thou not be angry towards vs, till thou hadſt conſumed vs, ſo that ther ſhold be no remain or ſcaping? ô Lord God of Iſrael, in ſo doing thou ſhouldſt be iuſt: yet we are reſerued to eſcape, as appeareth this day. Behold we are before thee in our treſpaſſes, our conſcience doth acknowlege the ſame: haue mercy vppon vs, for we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand before thee, becauſe of it. O that it woulde pleaſe God to mooue you our moſt dread ſoueraign, after this manner to go into God his houſe again, with ESDRAS and acknowledge this ouerſight with tears! Then would a great aſſembly of all ſorts of people of this land be gathered about you with weeping and great lamentation. Then wold your honorable counſell come about
<pb facs="tcp:11944:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>you, as SECHANIAH the ſonne of IEHIHEL came to ESDRAS, and ſaid, we haue treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt God, by receiuing a ſtrange mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery; yet there is hope concerning this. Now therfore let vs make a couenant with our God and put away this dumb miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp; place in their room a godly preaching miniſtery, according to the counſell of the Lord, and thoſe that feare the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our God, and let it be done accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the law. Ariſe, the matter belongeth vnto thee, we alſo will be with thee. Be of good comfort and do it. But the means how this learned miniſtery may be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, are beſt known vnto your wiſdomes. But if you will giue vs countrimen leaue to ſhew our opinions with patience. Briefely we think, there muſt be a ſufficient number of workmen, and honeſt prouiſion be made for them, as we read that SOLOMON, for the building of the materiall temple, found out 183300 able men that were occupied in hewing of ſtone and timber, and carrying of burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which al were maintained at the king his coſt, yet we think that a leſſe num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of work-men would ſuffice for the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this ſpirituall Temple, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, is farre more glorious then
<pb facs="tcp:11944:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>SOLOMON his temple. If it be ſayd the ſmall number of skilfull men canne not eaſilye be founde, a lamentable thing to be heard. What ſhoulde we do? but firſt place all thoſe worthy men, that can be found, and erect more Colledges and ſeminaries of true religion, to enlarge the kingdome of Chriſt: as we ſee Antichriſt, whoſe talents are as hard as braſſe, to hold faſt whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer commeth within them, &amp; whoſe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is as inſatiable, as hell, yet doth hee ſpare no coſt to build Seminaries of lyes and hereſies, to aduaunce the kingdome of the Deuill, who by ſuch means, hath great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preuayled in this land: Should then the pillers of the kingdome of Chriſt be more ſparing, yea, more colde to prouyde all thinges neceſſary for the Lordes army, to be ſent againſt theſe Idolatoures, with a two edged Sworde in their handes, to execute vengeaunce vppon theſe and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection againſte the people, to caſt downe imaginations, and euery high thing, that is exalted againſt the knowledge of God, and to bring into captiuity euery thought, to the obedience of CHRISTE? God forbid. For, if the enemy hath encreaſed his force, Is it not meete, that we ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:11944:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>doubt oures? Nowe for the prouiſion of ſuche a number of able men as mighte come out of Colledges and other ſchools of Learning, to take charge vppon them; This Noble Iſelande may not for ſhame complayne, of want: For the Lorde his eyes are vppon this Lande Nighte and Daye, that it is as fruitefull as the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dene of EDEN, a Parragonne of all the Worlde, and the Store-houſe for other Countryes: The wealth whereof is ſo greate, that menne, and Women can not deuyſe to waſte it vaynelye. Then when the Lorde ſayth that hee hathe neede of mayntaynaunce for his Miniſters; Shall wee ſaye that wee haue it not? In the time of Idolatrye there was more then ſufficiente by farre. Howe then is it em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſeled awaye, that there is not to feede CHRISTE, and too cloath him? Howe canne wee ſaye, that wee loue him? no, not ſo muche as Antichriſte loueth the Deuill: For Antichriſte is bountifull, to mayntayne his ſeruice. If the like libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality were vſed amongeſt vs, without all doubt, a greate number woulde be ſtayed, from paſſing the ſeas to Rome or Rhemes to become Ieſuites.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11944:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>What is then to be done? Giue vnto God that which belongeth to God, and vnto CAESAR that which belongeth vnto CAE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SAR. What belongeth to God, that is kept from him? euen that which appertaineth vnto his church, to wit, preſentations and impropriations. That things pertayning to the church, do alſo belong to the Lorde, it appeareth in the prophet MALACHIE, cap 3. Where he him ſelf doth ſeriouſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne, ſaying: Will a man ſpoyl his Gods? yet haue ye ſpoiled me. But ye ſay, wherin haue we ſpoiled thee? in tithes &amp; offerings, ye are curſed, with a curſe, for ye haue ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me, euen this whole nation? Hath not the whole nation of England ſpoyled the Lord in like manner, and rather more: that a work-man his hire is to be found in few places. Surely, this is written for our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that we might know that things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to GOD for the ſeruice of his church belong vnto him for euer: as the tithes which were dedicated to the Lorde, and his church by our fore-fathers with great equity which by no right can be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away as we read Leui. 27. Nothing ſeperate from commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſe, that a man doth ſeperate vnto the Lord of all that he hath, (whether
<pb facs="tcp:11944:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>it be man or beaſt or land of his inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance may be ſold or redeemed. For euery thing ſeperate from the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſe is moſt holy vnto the Lord. The which law, is not ceremoniall but iudiciall: the equity wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of endureth to the church for euer, and the violation of the ſame law hath bene horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly puniſhed in former dais, as we read that ACHAN who defrauded the Lord of ſiluer &amp; gold conſecrated to his treaſury, was put to death with al his houſ in a fearful maner, NABVCHADNEZER alſo ſpoiled the temple of the holy veſſels, conſecated to the Lords ſeruice, which BALTHASAR alſo abuſed by drinking wine in them with his concubines turning holithings to prophane vſes, whoſe heauy iudgement was not deferred, the like we read of Ananias &amp; Saphira his wife, who ſold a parcell of land, &amp; dedicated the price thereof to God &amp; his church. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei had conſented to keepe part of that which was conſecrated, they werſharply rebuked by Peter, and ſodainly ſtriken to death. The like iuſtice can no man eſcape, either in this world, or in the world to come, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the like offence, for the Lord is not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall in iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, neither with him is there any reſpect of perſons, but he that ſinnrth
<pb facs="tcp:11944:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhall die the death, except he turn vnto him with true repentance, &amp; reformation of his ſinnes, and aſſuredly the ſacriledge of holy things is committed euen with greedineſſe in this Land. Howe can Chriſte in the laſt day, place theſe men which commit ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and make the church ſo naked of her owne right hand, and ſay: I was hungry &amp; ye fed me, I was naked and ye clothed me; and not rather thruſt them among the Goats, on the left hand, ſaying, depart from me ye curſed into euerlaſting fire, prepared for the diuell and his angels: for I was hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and ye gaue me not mine own: I was naked and ye parted my garments among you. For whatſoeuer ye did vnto my poore miniſters in defrauding them, ye did to me. Yea let them take heede, leaſt in the day of their death, the Church doe not appeare in their conſciences, as a mighty ſea to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm them, and they ſay then: Come yee mountaines, and couer vs, that we may fly from the fearce wrath of the Lord, and not behold his fearfull countenance. For we muſt make reſtitution to the vttermoſt far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Repent threfore in time, and make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, as the lawe requireth. If any man by error hath taken, that which was holy to
<pb facs="tcp:11944:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Lorde: Let him reſtore it, and put the fift part to it according to the law. Leui. 27. Then ſhall Chriſt his ſacrifice be accepted for him. Which reſtitution, we read that ZACHEVS practized moſt ſtreightly: as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by his own wordes. If I haue done any man wrong, I will reſtore him foure folde, For repentance, without ſatisfaction if it be in thy power, is no better then plain mocking of God. And to mooue them the more, let them remember, what S. PAVLE wrighteth to the Corinths. Know ye not that the vniuſt ſhal not inherit the kingdom of God? What greater iniuſtice, then to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud God of his glory? the miniſters of their right? and the poore people of their euerlaſting life? But we truſt, that if certain, that do neither regard God nor his church, and therefore will not be willing to depart with any thing for the maintenance of a learned Miniſtery, that the good prince NEHEMIAH accompanied with ſo many worthy men, as are now aſſembled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, will diſapoint that prophane man TO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BIIAH, of his Iodging, in the cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the houſe of the Lord, and make it cleane for the Leuites. And this iniury if we feele, to be ſo great, to take that from vs, which we
<pb facs="tcp:11944:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>wold conſecrate to the food of our ſouls, &amp; yet we are vtterly famiſhed, that we think it not only manifeſt by the lawe of God, but alſo by the light of nature; yea, if they them ſelues, which haue theſe impropriatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s were depoſed vpon their oth, by their ſuperiors, whether in their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, they wrong the Church or no? they would firſt make many excuſes. But if they were vrged with an oth, ſurely they wold lay their handes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their mouth, &amp; craue pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may be couered, yet it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be vtterly extinguiſhed. Which light of nature ſhined moſt clearly in king Pharao, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the great famin of the land, hauing broght all the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the people, was ſo far off from ſeeking of the grounde belonging to the prieſtes, that to preſerue it, of his bountifulneſſe he gaue them, an ordinary alowance. If this heathen king had ſuch a conſcience, to preſerue the ſtate of his ſuperſtitious prieſtes, by relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them in the time of extremity, ſhould Chriſtian eſtates make leſſe conſcience, to maintaine the true ſeruants of God, which ſhewe vnto vs the way of ſaluation in the time of peace and proſperity. We pray you (right honourable) to ſpare vs to ſpeak a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more: for we pleade for the ſaluation of
<pb facs="tcp:11944:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>our ſouls. It ſeemeth vnto vs that Chriſt the grand captain of the tribe of Iuda, as one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken out of ſleepe, and as a ſtrong man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wine, doth now offer him ſelfe to ſmite his &amp; our enimies on the hinder parts, and to put them to a perpetual ſhame, requiring of you a number of expert ſouldiers, the maintenaunce for them, which are rights &amp; roialties of his kingdom, &amp; therefore iuſtly we cannot deny him. But if the patrone ſay that he will not loſe his patronage, for then he ſhould forgo his pillage, nor the impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietary wil diminiſh any of his impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the ſeruice of this war (of which diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſition we hope that ther is none among you) but that rather they woulde intreate Chriſt to depart the country as the Gerge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits did for the loſſe of their ſwine: or more ſpitefully repell him as the phariſeis, Who ſayd depart hence, or Herodes wil kil thee. Might he not conceiue ſuch griefe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt vs vpon this repulſe, who came to deliuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the greateſt bondage and ſlauery in the world, &amp; to enfranchiſe vs as the citizens of his kingdom the baſeſt of whom are Nobles and Princes? Might not this vnkinde acte (ſay wee) ſo much kyndle his diſpleaſure towardes vs, that
<pb facs="tcp:11944:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>he might be mooued to retire back with all his bleſſings, and turne them into plagues, againſt ſuch an vnkind people? what iniury then ſhould he offer vs? Surely none at all. But to diſcend to ſome particuler example of want of maintenance, as where a church is endowed with half that prouiſion which is requiſit to maintain a preacher, by reaſon of the impropriation, as it falleth out in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny churches of this land, which iniury was done by Antichriſt in the night, and now reſtitution might be made in the day: Yea, put the caſe that the church is not endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with value of 20. markes (as exceeding many churches haue leſſe) how canne we think that a learned man that hath ſpent many years in good letters, and in the holy ſcriptures, will ſeat him ſelf there, almoſt to famiſh him ſelf, &amp; not rather to employ his labour to the teaching of children? Then by meanes of this impropriation, ſuch a cleark as is correſpondent to the liuing ſhal be placed there, a man that can bring no glad tidings, and to be plain an idoll ſheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard: whereby of neceſſity it muſt fall out in that congregation, that HAGAR ſhall be fruitfull in bringing foorth bond-men and ſlaues vnto Sathan, and SARAH altogether
<pb facs="tcp:11944:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>barren. How then can that impropietory ſeeing this, eate ſauourly thoſe holy things heretofore conſecrated to the ſauing of ſouls without ſalt tears trickling down his cheeks (except his hart be as hard as braſſe) knowing that he is the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone, that doth ſhut the gate againſt the preacher, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly defraud God of his honor in that place, and kil the ſouls of a multitude of his poore neighbours, that would liue and not periſh. And this ſlaughter of ſoules likely to be continued thorow all poſterities, except reſtitution be made thereof to giue enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment to a preacher. And the which is more lamentable to be knowne, how many hirelings for fiue or ſixe poundes be in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Congregations in this Lande, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the North partes, where there is two or three thouſande ſoules of all ſortes of people both olde and young, that come to one Church to bee taught: where the poore ſilly man is as one that hath not fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his belly in many Weekes before, or lately come out of Pryſon, with a ſharpe face, both pale and white, who hath leſſe ſpirituall food to feed the people that flock about him, then he hath bodily nouriſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to fill their bellies: ſo that in ſuch a popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb facs="tcp:11944:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>congregation, ther be 3. or 4. that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to giue an account of their faith, it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much, and yet that worke is wrought by ſome extraordinary hand of God, &amp; not to be imputed to the ſeely body. And thus it falleth out in many places where there bee farmers to her maieſty of impropriations that as they are careles for the peoples ſouls &amp; their owne, the like regard haue they to maintain the building of the cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels, which lye ruinous in ſundry places, quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to her maieſties pleaſure, &amp; the good pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niworth they haue at her gratious handes. Theſe &amp; other thinges cauſe vs to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the daies of HEEI; wherin ther was no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt viſion. For the 2. ſons of HELY, OPH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NY &amp; PHINIAS who knewe not the Lorde were wicked men alſo, cauſed the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael to abhor the offerings of the Lord, &amp; the ſeruice of their God. By whoſe meanes the people treſpaſſed grieuouſly againſt the Lord in negligence, or rather contempt of comming to the tabernacle to worſhip the Lord according to the law. Of which diſho nor of God, HELY being informed that his ſons were the occaſion thereof, yet did not reform &amp; redreſſe that great miſchief, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that authority &amp; power, which hee had being cheefe iudge &amp; high prieſt of the
<pb facs="tcp:11944:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>people, but only gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; wheras their fault &amp; offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce deſerued rather to bee puniſhed with death. For whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſnes or rather negligence to reform ſuch a waighty matter, the Lord threatned ſuch a grieuous plague &amp; deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him &amp; vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his houſe, which was truly executed as the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance therof doth make ears to tingle. So the contempt &amp; corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the worſhip of God, remaining vnreformed, at laſt it came to paſſe, the ſins of the prieſts &amp; of the people were grieuouſly puniſhed by a gret ſlaughter, which they ſuſtained of the philiſtims, &amp; the ark of the Lord taken away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the midſt of them &amp; deliuered into the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of their enimies. In ſteed of Ophny &amp; Phineas, we haue a ſwarme &amp; multitude of miniſters that neither in ignoraunce of the Lord, nor in lewd behauior are inferiour to them. By whoſe ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; wickednes the admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the word &amp; ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſaboth day is by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> greatly prophaned, &amp; of the people grieuouſly conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned. Which prophanatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that ſacred day, if it ſhould not be reformed, it were to bee feared that by theſe idol miniſters &amp; we the people of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending together with them likewiſe, ſhold fal into the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of our enimies the papiſts, &amp; the word of God taken from vs, which is
<pb facs="tcp:11944:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>more deare and precious vnto vs then was the arke of the couenant vnto the Iſraelits. But we truſt that theſe euils ſhall not come vpon vs, becauſe that for the redres of this hainous corruption of the ſeruice of God, we make our complaint vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue equal authoritie with HELY, &amp; greater zele to aduance the honor of God, and to wipe away the deformities of his church; whoſe hearts do tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble at the words of the Lord, who as we are perſwaded wil not be perta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers with HELY in his ſins, leſt they ſhould alſo be pertakers with him in his terrible puniſhments. Therfore ſith ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes of vs be in ſuch a ſtreite by meanes hereof, not poſſible for vs by any meanes we can eſpy either now or hereafter to be deliuered without your gratious &amp; mighty helping hands: haue pity vpon vs right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable aſſembly, &amp; let our ſoules be preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in your ſight. Let vs not die that euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting death like fooles in Iſrael, but ſo worke in this Parliament, that you may ſay vnto the people of the whole lande: Wee take you to record this day, that wee are pure from the bloud of al men, for we haue kept nothing backe, but haue eſtabliſhed al ſuch lawes as are neceſſary for the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing
<pb facs="tcp:11944:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>of all the counſels of God vnto you his people. For al the whole land is at your commandement both of body and goods (with the conſent of our moſt gratious ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraign, who is full of mercy and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) to do as by law you ſhal preſcribe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And aſſuredly (right honourable) it were better for vs by farre (if no other remedie could be had) to liue with bread and water in the wilderneſſe with the Iſraelites all the dayes of our miſerable life, with the plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful preaching of the word of God, then to haue our welfare (which we acknowledge to be great) a thouſands time doubled with this great famiſhment of the worde, which we endure in the moſt places of this land: for then our miſery after a ſmal time would end in felicitie: where as now our mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary pleaſure wil ſhortly be turned into we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth, except the Lord come downe from heauen to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit vs by your miniſtery. We pray you ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt pitifully (right honourable) that that voice may no more be heard amongſt vs. The Lordes houſe cannot be built in many places within this land for want of prouiſion: for that doth kil our hearts alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as if you ſhould ſay vnto vs: There
<pb facs="tcp:11944:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>is no remedy but you muſt needes die in your ſinnes and ignorance, the ſecond and euerlaſting death. O moſt doleful voice, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to breake the Adamant, &amp; to reſolue it into teares; which terrible voice the Lord of his infinite mercy turne farre away from vs. But vndoubtedly ſo godly and religious an aſſembly, the faire flowers of this land, will neuer ſpeake ſo hardly vnto vs; but (we hope) the contrary ſaying. This houſe may be built in thoſe deſolate places, and with Gods helpe and our ſoueraignes it ſhall be built, &amp; therefore poore people be of good comfort. Otherwiſe you ſhould beare grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter blame then the poore Iewes that came out captiuity from Babilon, &amp; differred the building of the materiall temple, excuſing the matter, that it was not yet time to build it; and neuer ſaid, that by reaſon of their great pouerty &amp; multitude of their enemies that it could not be built at all. Thus right honourable, we haue bewraied our griefe, made our petition known, declared the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments of a lerned miniſtery, &amp; ſhewed that an honeſt maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: Looke vpon vs; lift vp your eies &amp; behold a great multitude gathered about you, which are in the wildernes &amp; haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:11944:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>to eate. Be moued with compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs, for we are as ſheepe wanting a ſhepheard. We are hungry &amp; come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> far; we come vnto you as children vnto the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and aske bread, we truſt you will not giue vs a ſtone; we craue a fiſh, will you in ſteade of a fiſh giue vs a ſerpent? we deſire to haue an egge; ſurely you wil not giue vs a ſcorpion. O let vs liue and not diel &amp; let not that lamentable weeping and howling be heard among vs in the countrey, which ſometime was heard in Ramah. Let vs not bewaile the ſpirituall death of our children &amp; poſteritie, as RACHEL wept for the bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly death of her children who could not be comforted, becauſe they were not. But let the ſiluer trump of the Lord ſound the law in our eares, to the caſting down of the old man, and the goſpel to the raiſing vp of the new ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Let the Lords lights be placed in our temples, &amp; then ſhal it be fulfilled again which was ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the Prophet. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which ſate in darknes, ſaw a great light; &amp; to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſate in the regio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſhadow of death, light is riſen vp. And therefore we humbly beſeech you right honourable to ſtir vp you tender affections towardes ſuch a multitude of vs ſimple people that are in
<pb facs="tcp:11944:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>this land fleeting in the ſea of ſinne and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and now vpon ſight of comfort, making an outcry for the ſafety of our life. That it would pleaſe you to reach foorth your right hand of mercy, &amp; by your godly wiſdomes to eſtabliſh the means of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance, for we are in your handes either to ſaue or ſpil. And therfore, if there ſhould be ſome of you that would not further to the vttermoſt this the weightieſt cauſe of a thouſand, concerning not onely our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but more the glory of Chriſt. Howe could theſe men proteſt that he loued him, ſeing he hath ſet ouer the triall of his loue to the care of the feeding of his flocke? As he hath manifeſtly declared in the perſon of PETER, ſaying: Loueſt thou me; feede my ſheepe, feede my lambes. And though you feede them not in your owne perſons; yet ye feede them in procuring them to be fedde: for the which cauſe ye are called by the Lord, the Paſtours and ſhepeheards of the people. Moreouer, if theſe men ſhould haue any ſuite to the father of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, for any thing wherof they ſhold ſtand in need; how could they vſe Chriſt as a mediatour and aduocate, to bring their matters to good effect, if they ſhould neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
<pb facs="tcp:11944:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuch a weightie cauſe of his, which he deſireth ſo earneſtly to be brought to paſſe, as appeareth when he ſaith: Firſt, ſeeke the kingdom of God, and the righteouſneſſe thereof, &amp;c. Which is chiefly performed by a learned miniſterie, &amp; not rather be afraid to heare his voice. They that honour me, will I honor, and they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be deſpiſed. But be it farre from vs to think any thing but good of ſo honorable aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: for we hope that our mouth ſhall bee filled with laughter, &amp; our tong with ioy, ſaying: The Lord hath done great things for vs, wherof we may reioyce. When we remember your pitifull inclination vppon complaint made, to redreſſe all maner of, yea, ſmalleſt iniuries touchyng this lyfe. How ſhold we now doubt to be ſent emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty away, when we come for matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning euerlaſting life. We come therfore vnto you in great bitterneſſe of our ſoules, not able to expreſſe halfe the grief we feele for the death of our ſonnes &amp; daughters, as the Sunamite came to ELIZEVS for the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily death of her ſonne, praying you to ſend ELIZEVS and the ſonnes of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, to ſpred themſelues vpon vs, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to breathe into vs the word
<pb facs="tcp:11944:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>of life, and to make prayers and ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to God forvs; ſo by litle there is hope that we ſhal be reuiued again into a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all life: for ſurely GEHEZY by laying on vs ELIZEVS his ſtaffe, we meane theſe hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, by reading to vs their Homelies, can do vs no good. For notwithſtanding this ſtaffe GEHEZY may returne anſwere, that we can neither ſpeake nor heare, which be euident tokens of want of life. We beſeech you in Chriſt his name to take our ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation as the man of Macedonia, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared vnto PAVL in a viſion, praying you to ſend preachers into our country to help vs, and in ſo doing be you wel aſſured that you paſſe not the bounds of your vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Oh, that you were caried in a viſion into ſome great high mountaine, and could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the huge army of people of this land ſpiritually ſlaine of Sathan more cruelly &amp; pitifully then euer was ſlaine, as we ſuppoſe in the greateſt battel that euer was ſince the creation of this world. Then would you ſhed teares aboundantly with our Sauiour Chriſt, who ſtanding vpon mount Oliuet, beheld that ſtubburne city of Ieruſalem &amp; wept for them, becauſe thei refuſed the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of ſaluation then offered them. But
<pb facs="tcp:11944:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>our caſe is to bee bewailed and pitied, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the doctrine of ſaluation is not offred vs by the way of preaching, in ſo many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueral congregations, as hunger and thirſt after it. And therefore hearken what Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba ſaith to euery one of you. Open thy mouth for the dumbe, in the cauſe of al the children of deſtruction, ſo ſhall you be able to ſay with Iob to your vnſpeakeable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort after this maner. When the eare heard me, it bleſſed me, and when the eye ſaw me, it gaue witneſſe to me, for I deliuered the poore that cried, and the fatherleſſe, &amp; him that had none to helpe him. The bleſſing of him that was ready to periſh, came vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, and I cauſed the widowes heart to reioyce: I brake alſo the iawes of the vnrighteous, &amp; pluckt the praie out of his teeth. Now then there is no time of ſilence, your vocation will not ſuffer it, but that euery one of you without exceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, all excuſes ſet apart, is to extend his voice, wit, authoritie &amp; credit to the vttermoſt degree in the cauſe of Chriſt &amp; his church, pleding it (if need ſo require) ſo zealouſly vntil you ſweat &amp; faint withal, ſeeing that in your cauſe Chriſt refuſed not to ſweat drops of bloud. But as the Lord is kind to thoſe that deale kindly with him:
<pb facs="tcp:11944:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo his diſpleaſure is death, if he being e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected or contemned. Know him therfore and his cauſe, that hee may know you as his friends in the day of his glory. And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that Chriſt that maketh this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt for a learned miniſtery, (which by his authority he might command, but rather thorough loue he entreateth you by vs) is not more vile and contemptible, but glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſitting on the right hand of his father, and therefore is able, and will requite this kindneſſe done to him ſeuen fold into your boſome: yea, the Lord will account it to be kindneſſe, although in all right and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, it is an homage moſt iuſtly appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to his roialty, by reaſon that we hold of him, al that euer we haue in Capite. And though you be willing to perform this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, yet let vs put you in remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that Sathan will withſtand you, with all his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and power, who is the prince of this worlde, and therefore will not ſuffice him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be throwne out of his kingdome, as appeareth in the deliuerance of the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael, from vnder the hand of Pharaoh in reedifiyng of the primatiue Church: ſo at this preſent day, he is not altered, either
<pb facs="tcp:11944:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>in myght or malice, that he will be content to reſigne his kingdome ouer vnto Chriſt; but as then, ſo now with all ſpeede wyll he muſter his men of warre againſt thoſe that attempt to the aboliſhing of his kingdome. Then we are to know, that as no victory is gotten without ſtrife, much leſſe noble vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory without contention in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree: For it is to be feared, that the diuell, the fleſh and the world, will all oppoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt you, which notwithſtandyng beyng atchieued, is farre more glorious in the high court of heauen, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the conqueſt of ten mighty kingdoms made tributary &amp; vaſſals vnto this land. This therefore is a worke worth the trial of your ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnanimitie, ioyned with the greateſt honor that may be. So that if you preuayle (right honorable) as we truſt your enemies ſhall fall downe before you, otherwyſe we could ſee no ende of our griefe and ſorow, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no doubt in the iudgement of all wiſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, you ſhall be counted comparable with the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of the world: yea, farre paſſing them in all true honour and glory. And ſeyng we haue begun to ſpeake to the right honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſembly, beyng but the baſe people of the land: Let it not diſpleaſe you that wee
<pb facs="tcp:11944:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpeake yet a litle more: But if any thing ſhal eſcape our penne vnfit to be ſpoken by vs to ſo high and honourable a courte of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, we moſt humbly beſeech you vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our knees by the price of the death and paſſion of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and by his glorious commyng to iudgement for our euerlaſtyng deliueraunce, to pardon vs, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting it eyther to the griefe and bitternes of our ſoules, which cauſed IOB to vtter ſome fooliſh wordes; or to the rudeneſſe of our education, whereby in woordes and termes we may fayle againſt our will. For our purpoſe is (God knoweth) not to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our ſuite by offending any, but by a plaine and pitiful manifeſtation of the truth to winne the fauor of you all in this weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and long deſirous petition, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the ſaluation of our ſoules. But to the matter. We haue heard it ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by wiſe men, and it ſinketh deeply into our minds, that if euery one of you were in pollicie comparable to ACHITOPHEL the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonite, whoſe aduiſe for the common welth in the dayes of DAVID, was taken as an oracle of God, yet if you ſhould deuiſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtrong lawes for the preſeruation of her maieſties perſon (whom the Lord bleſſe for
<pb facs="tcp:11944:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>euer) the peace and proſperitie of this land, and the ſubuerſion of our enemies the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Ieſuites, &amp; paſſe ouer this law for a learned miniſtery (by planting whereof we are ſure to haue a perpetuall league of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie with the Father, the Sonne, the holy Ghoſt and mighty angels of heauen, who wil be vnto vs a ſtrong wall of defence, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wherewith Babylon was enuironed, which was very ſtrong as the learned ſay: For if God be on our ſide, who can bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs.) Then (ſay they) that thoſe good lawes would be as weake and fraile to bind faſt the head ſtrong papiſts and Ieſuites, as were the 7. greene withs neuer dried, and the new ropes neuer occupied able to bind mighty SAMSON. But being ioyned with that principal lawe, they will be as ſharpe as a raſor to cut them cleane of. But as in the greateſt miſchiefs viz. by waſting by fire &amp; water, as alſo by the inuaſion of the enemy, the Prouerbe hath place, Delay doth make the danger greater: ſo eſpecially it holdeth in the inuaſion of the greateſt enemy of all mankinde, who hath already taken many townes and caſtles in this land, ſhewing all kind of tiranny whereſoeuer he commeth. Therefore as when the bodily enemies
<pb facs="tcp:11944:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>enter the land to waſte and deſtroy the care full magiſtrates, ſet the beacons on fire, whereby with all ſpeede they leuy power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the enemy, leaſt by ſuffrance &amp; daily victories, he ſhould make himſelf ſo ſtrong, that afterwards he were not able to bee dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen out of the countrey. So the like expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or rather greater, were to be vſed in ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering an army of woorthy ſouldiours to encounter Sathan before he enlarge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the kingdome of darkenes by means of theſe Ieſuites, leaſt as we haue ſeene with our eyes in the dayes of Queene MARY, it might fal out by the iuſt iudgement of God for our ſinnes, that by tract of time he might poſſeſſe the whole kingdome, as the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd Ieſuites, his faythfull ſeruauntes, doe endeuour to bryng to paſſe. And therfore, as you loue the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and hys Church, which is as tender vnto hym, as the apple of his eye, in the preparation of his warrefare, deale not ſparingly or nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardly with hym, but honour hym with your ſubſtaunce as hee requireth, who hath beene ſo riche and bountifull to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes you not onely in the treaſures of the kyngdome of Heauen, but alſo in the bleſſinges of this preſentlyfe. So that the
<pb facs="tcp:11944:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lorde hath not ſet you belowe, but hath placed you on high: And if that whiche hee hath done for you bee too little, hee will yet multiply his graces vppon you, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till you runne ouer. O remember and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not that ſeeing Chriſt the Sonne of the liuing God, equall with his Father, aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in loue towards you, did caſt aſide all honor and glory, and made him ſelf of no reputation, by taking vpon him the forme of a ſeruant: yea, he became a worme and no man: a very abiect of the people, to raiſe from the duſt, and to lifte you oute of the dung, to cauſe you to ſit with princes of his people in the heauenly places in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: he alſo became pore, not hauing wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon to lay his hed, to make you to abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in thoſe moſte excellent riches, which the eye hath not ſeene, nor the eare hath not heard, neyther haue they entred into the hearte of any carnall man. Ought you not with like recompence of loue towards him to lay your honor and riches at his feete to couer the ſhame and nakedneſſe of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate Church? if ye proteſt in worde that loue him, &amp; that yee are deſirous to ſee the Church his ſpouſe in her glorious beauty, arrayed in robes of needle worke: yea, clad
<pb facs="tcp:11944:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>with a veſture of Gold of Ophire, &amp; yet wil not deſcend one ſtep downeward, or abaſe your ſelfe one whit, nor open youre purſes to contribute releefe, euen to ſuſtaine her neceſſities, but keeping backe her ancient reuenewes, wherewith heeretofore ſhe was furniſhed to all neceſſary vſes: how can this fayned loue eſcape the ſharp cenſure of the apoſtle IAMES, who ſayth, if a brother or a ſiſter be naked and deſtitute of daily food, and one of you ſaye vnto them, departe in peace, warme your ſelues and fill your bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, notwithſtanding yee giue them not thoſe things, which are needeful to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, what helpeth it, but we are fully perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that theſe rich mercies of Ieſus Chriſte cannot lye hid and reſt in the heart of anye man liuing, but that they wil kindle a flame of burning loue which will ſhewe it ſelfe bountifull and liberall to the aduancement of his Church and kingdome. And further whereas it hath beene prouided by a good ſtatute, that a freedome from paymente of tythes for a certaine time ſhould be graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them that doe conuert barren and waſte grounde into tillage, to giue them a greater encouragement to take the toyle in hand; &amp; that ye haue likewiſe bin careful to
<pb facs="tcp:11944:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>prouide for the tuing of Marſhes, that haue bene ouerflowen &amp; ſurrownded with water: oughte not then a farre greater care and diligence be vſed that a wiſe and ſure Lawe mighte bee eſtabliſhed to bring the Lordes Feelde into Tillage whiche lyeth waſte and barren of the fruites of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and full of thornes and bryers fit for nothing but for the fire, and is likewiſe drowned with the flowds of ſinne and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce, as it is pittifullye to bee ſeene in the greateſt parte of this Lande: whiche Lawe if it ſhoulde bee neglected, ſeeing it concerneth peace and proſperitye of oure ſoules for euer, ſhoulde not iuſt occaſion bee giuen to take vppe this Prouerbe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte you? They haue ſtrayned a Gnatte and ſwallowed a Camell: but wee truſt that the Lorde in his mercye will looke vpon vs, and ſtir vp in the hearts of ſo graue Wiſe, and Godlye a Senate, ſuche a care and pitty ouer vs, that none of the euilles which we feare ſhall fall vpon vs. For as we wee reade that when DAVID had built him ſelfe an houſe in Ieruſalem, yet ſwore hee vnto the Lorde, and vowed to the mighty God of IAACOB, ſaying, I will not enter into the Tabernacle of myne
<pb facs="tcp:11944:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>houſe, nor come vpon my pallet or bed, nor ſuffer mine eyes to ſleepe, nor mine eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids to ſlumber, vntill I finde out a place for the Lord, an habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the mighty God of IAACOB. So if you all as one man, in like godly zeale with DAVID, ſhould ſweare &amp; vowe vnto the Lorde that you woulde not not return vnto thoſe fayre houſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Lorde hath bleſſed you, to take your comfort, and recreation therin, vntill ſuch time, as you haue prouided and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, not that the Arke of the Lorde, but that the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, which is a more ſure token of his preſence, ſhould bee brought into his Temple, and placed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Cherubins, which thing is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed when the Goſpell is committed to a faythfull Miniſterye of the Lorde, to whome al the people may reſort, in doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cauſes to aske Counſell of God. But contrariwiſe, nothing leſſe is doone when the Goſpell of reconcilliation is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into handes of a dumb &amp; idoll miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who can neyther open the booke nor ſhut it: neither by the authority thereof can eyther binde or looſe. Who are to bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed not to medle with that ſacred booke as publike perſons, leaſt the Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:11944:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>make a breach into them as he did into VZ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZA. Aſſuredly in this youre ſeruice of the Lord, ye ſhould do a work worthy of al po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities to be remembred: ſo ſhoulde it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that ye are not onelye carefull for the Churche in recommending her good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate by prayer vnto the Lord: ſaying, peace be within thy walles, and proſperity within thy pallaces: for my brethren and neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors ſakes, I will wiſh thee now proſperity, but alſo by deedes, when ye perfourme the ſame. As it is written, becauſe of the houſe of the Lorde our God, I will procure thy wealth. Conſider alſo that it was in the hart of DAVID, to build a temple vnto the Lord but becauſe hee was occupied in warres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the enimies of the lord, the building of that houſe was committed vnto his Son SOLOMON: To whome the Lord promiſed peace from his enimies on euery ſide: ſo he broughte the worke, to perfection in the fourth yeare of his raigne. Shoulde we not thinke, that ſeeing the Lorde hath bleſſed vs with the peace of SOLOMON in the time of the Goſpell for the ſpace of twenty ſeuen yeares, that it had beene our duetye with like diligence and ſpeede, to haue ſet vp the Spirituall Temple of the Lorde in a
<pb facs="tcp:11944:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>glorious beauty, ſo that hardly any default or blemiſh could by this time haue bene e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpied in the ſame: yea, hathe not the Lorde ſhewed himſelf angry againſt the whol la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and thretned a grieuous puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t againſt it when he hath at ſundry times offred dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger vnto her maieſty, by the ſons of Beliall, as though he would quench the light of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael? yet the Lord with great patience hath had mercy, not only on her, but alſo on vs, ſtill waiting, if now at the laſt, we wil reform and amend ſuch grieuous ruin amongſt vs. And we beſeech you to caſt your eies from Dan to Berſheba, and ſee if there be any ſin more deteſtable and odious in the ſight of the Lord that raigneth in this land, then the permiſſion of this idoll miniſtery: whereby the people periſh without number, &amp; God is defrauded of his honor. And if any man be wilfully ignorant in theſe things, let him be ignorant ſtill, for the Lorde hath reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it vnto babes, yet if any man will nowe commend the ſtate of the Church compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with that time wherein the palpable darkneſſe of Aegypt couered the land (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture to ſtay the proceedinges of the godly minded) we acknowledge it with all thankeſgiuing vnto God, to be excellent &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:11944:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſingular. But if we compare our Church by that which the Lord requireth in his word, and we by duty are bound to performe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a great penalty layd vpon vs, which the long peace and quietneſſe of this Lande might haue made eaſy to be perfourmed &amp; the examples of the other countries haue prouoked forward, we ſhall find the church to be in great weaknes and deſolation: So that we haue great cauſe of lamentation to ſee her thus lye in the duſt. For wee read in the Prophet Amos, that the Lord brought a greeuous plague vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael, which ought to haue cauſed them to return vnto the Lord, by withholding the rain fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth, ſo that it rained vpon one city &amp; not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another, one peece was rained vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; the pcece whervpon it rained not, withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: ſo 2. or 3. cities wandered vnto one city to drink Water, but they were not ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: hath not this plague twiſe doubled, fallen vppon vs cauſe vs to turne vnto the the Lorde, ſeeing hee hath reſtrained the dewe of his Worde, euen the Water of life, from falling vppon manye Townes of the Countrye, ſo that tenne or twelue of them ſhoulde bee compelled to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vnto one Towne in ſundrye places
<pb facs="tcp:11944:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>of this lande, if they had that godly deſire and thirſt of the worde which is required: yet peraduenture they ſhould not be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in that place. Then ſeing that the hand of the Lorde lyeth ſo grieuouſly vppon vs, ought we not to humble our ſelues in deep repentance with many tears, that the fierce wrath of the Lord may be turned away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, leaſt he adde plague vnto plague vntill we bee all conſumed from the face of the earth. But if it bee further prouided that hereafter men ſhall bee admitted into the miniſtery, except thoſe which are able to preach the worde of God, and that in the meane tyme we ſhall be contented to ſuffer thoſe idoll miniſters which are already en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the flocke, to weare out their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable days amongſt vs, then this miſchief perchaunce would driue vs to theſe extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, eyther to wiſhe that we had not as yet bene borne in the world, or els that ſome vntimely death ſodainly fall vppon theſe idols, leaſt the moſt part of vs ſhould be plunged in the deepe pit of hell, before their curſed dayes were ended. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the occaſion of theſe vnnatural deſires ought not to be enforced vpon vs, neither is there the like reaſon to make prouiſion in
<pb facs="tcp:11944:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>the matters of ſaluation onely, agaynſt the euils and miſchiefes which may happen af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that tyme, as it is conueniently done in the ciuil cauſes appertaining to this preſent life, for two waightie reaſons that may bee alleaged. Firſt, in ciuil matters, the euils and diſcommodities which are paſt, are ſuch, as are intollerable, and may be ſuffred, &amp; time will weare them away. Secondly, the peace of the publique wealth is preferred, and no man hath cauſe to complaine that any right is taken from him, but it is farre otherwyſe in this cauſe that concerneth the kingdom of heauen: for this miſchieuous euill of a blind miniſtery, is euery waies intollerable, for it is written: If the blind lead the blind, they ſhal both fall into the ditch, out of the which they can neuer riſe agayne, where there is weepyng, wayling and gnaſhyng of teeth for euer. For who is able to giue a ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to redeeme their ſoules out of hell, &amp; no length of tyme doeth weare away their miſery, but rather doth increaſe and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the anguiſh of their ſouls, neither is our peace diſturbed by remedying theſe euils that are paſt. For how can there be peace o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe eſtabliſhed before that this wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes as it were of ACAN that troubleth
<pb facs="tcp:11944:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>all Iſrael be taken away from amongeſt vs: And theſe blind guides haue leſt of al cauſe to complaine of iniury offred them, for by remoouing them out of their places, they ſhould receiue the greateſt benefite that could happen vnto them: for they ſhould bee forced to ceaſe from murdering Gods people any more, and if it were poſſible be brought to repentance for the giltineſſe of that bloud which they haue ſhed vpon the earth, that their ſoules might bee ſaued in that great day when the Lord ſhall come to iudgement: among which perſons (with your patience) the non reſidents are to bee numbred. And therfore we pray you right honorable in the tender mercies of Chriſt Ieſus, to redreſſe theſe euils that do preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hang vpon vs and oppreſſe vs with intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable bondage and ſlauery, no, not by the way of imagination any way ſuffrable. And looke round about you, and take for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to imitate, ſo many as haue bin zealous for the houſe of God, and liberall toward the maintenance thereof. Firſt, ſet God him ſelfe before your eyes, who in mount Sinai prouided a ſufficient portion to be giuen to the Leuites his miniſters to attend vppon holy things. Remember that the Iſraelites
<pb facs="tcp:11944:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>in their poore eſtate in the wildernes, gaue voluntarily more then inough, to the ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctyng of the Tabernacle and furniture thereof. But to paſſe ouer many exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples which might bee ſet before your eyes, let not EZECHIAS, IOSIAS, NE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HEMIAS, and the Princes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that bee vnder them be cleane forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Yea, CYRVS an Heathen king, and other Kinges of Perſia, were bountifull to the Temple of the Lorde. Of all which worthy men, the memory will euer flouriſh and neuer dye. But eſpecially, we beſeech our gracious and noble Princeſſe, to match her ſelfe with DAVID the chiefeſt woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the world, and not onely conſecrate the moſt iuſt ſpoiles of her enemies, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo giue bountifully of her owne peculiar treaſure to the mainteuaunce of the houſe of GOD after his example, and takyng vppon her his perſone, to come into this honourable aſſemblie of Parliament, and ſaye vnto them: This ſpirituall Temple is a great and mightye woorke, For this houſe is not for manne, but for GOD; Now I haue prepared with all my power for the houſe of my God: gold for veſſels of golde, and ſiluer for veſſelles of ſiluer,
<pb facs="tcp:11944:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>and braſſe for thinges of braſſe, yron for thinges of yron, and Wood for thinges of Wood, and onix ſtones and ſtones to bee ſet, and carbuncle ſtones, and of diuers co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and all precious ſtones, and marble ſtones in abundance. Moreouer, becauſe I haue delight in the houſe of my GOD, I haue of mine owne gold, and ſiluer, which I haue giuen to the houſe of God beſide all that I haue prepared for the houſe of my God, I haue prepared for the houſe of the ſanctuary, euen three thouſand talentes of of golde, of the gold of Ophir, and ſeuen thouſand talents of fined Siluer, to ouerlay the walles of the houſes. The golde for the things of gold, and the ſiluer for the things of ſiluer, and for all the worke by the hands of artificers, and who is willing to fill his hand to day vnto the Lorde. So the princes of the Families, and the princes of the tribes of Iſraell, and the captaines of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands and of hundreths, which the rulers of the king his work offered willingly &amp; they gaue for the ſeruice of the houſe of God, fiue thouſand talentes of gold, &amp; ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand peeces, and ten thouſand talents of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, &amp; eighteene thouſand talents of braſſe, and one hundreth talentes of yron. And
<pb facs="tcp:11944:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>with whom precious ſtones were founde, gaue them to the treaſure of the houſe of the Lord by the hand of IEHIEL the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonite. And the people reioiced whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they offred willingly: for they offred willingly vnto the Lorde with a perfect heart. And DAVID the king alſo reioyced with great ioy. Therfore DAVID bleſſed the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the congregation, and DAVID ſaid. Bleſſed be thou, ô Lord God of Iſrael, our father for euer and euer. Thine ô Lord is greatnes, and power, and glory, and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and prayſe, for all that is in heauen, and earth is thine: Thine is the kingdome, ô Lord, and thou excelleſt as head ouer all. Both riches and honour come of thee, and thou raigneſt ouer all, and in thyne hand is power, and ſtrength: and in thine hand it is to make great, and to giue ſtrength vnto all. Now therfore our God, we thank thee, and prayſe thy glorious name. But who am I? and what is my people, that we ſhould be able to offer willingly after this ſort? for all things come of thee; &amp; of thine owne hand we haue giuen thee: For we are ſtraungers before thee, and ſoiourners, like all our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: Our dayes are like the ſhadow vpon the earth, &amp; there is none abiding: ô Lord
<pb facs="tcp:11944:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>our God in al this abundance, that we haue prepared, to build thee an houſe for thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name, is of thine hande, and all is thine. I know alſo my God, that thou trieſt the hart, and haſt pleaſure in righteouſneſſe: I haue offred willingly in the vprightneſſe of mine heart all theſe things: now alſo haue I ſeen thy people which are found here to offer vnto thee willingly with ioy, ô Lord God ABRAHAM, IZZAK, and ISRAEL our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, keepe this for euer in purpoſe, and the thoughtes of the heart of thy people, and prepare their hearts vnto thee. And giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to SOLOMON my Sonne a perfect heart, to keepe thy commaundementes, thy teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and thy ſtatutes, and to do all thinges, and to build the houſe which I haue prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And DAVID ſayd vnto all the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. Nowe bleſſe the Lorde your God: And all the congregation bleſſed the Lord God of their fathers, and bowed downe their heads, and worſhipped the Lord, and the king. &amp;c. So ſhall our moſte gratious prince and her people, not onely in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation beholde this houſe, as DAVID did the other, but with SOLOMON alſo, ſee it erected, in al perfection, and reioyce won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfullye in the glorious beautye thereof.
<pb facs="tcp:11944:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>How much would this worthy worke ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce the honor of our Lord Chriſt? who no doubt, woulde honor you all againe in that great day, and make mention of this noble acte in that glorious aſſembly, to your vnſpeakeable comfort. Howe much ſhould you make the angels of God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce; who are glad at the conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of one ſinner? How many that remayne in their manifold ſinnes and ignorance, would the Lord conuert, if theſe workemen were ſent abroad to euery place? For the harueſt is great, and the laborers are few. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould the Lord his eyes be more vigilant to gard her royall perſon and the whole land. Then ſhould all the people bee knit together in one true religion, and be of one heart, and one ſoule, and not be caried away with the blaſt of euery Ieſuite, ſaying: Will you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the religion of your forefathers? Liued they not well? Had they not plenty of all things? For we thinke that nothing wil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy theſe vermine of the land without the plentiful preaching of the word. But beyng enriched therwith, we ſhould earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the Pope his traſh, and treade it vnder his feete as dung, which is now very ſalea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in this land. Then ſhould theſe Ieſuites
<pb facs="tcp:11944:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>be forced to cry as it were skrich owles not beyng able to abide the cleare light of the Goſpell, and flie into deſolate places, and mourne with the dragons at Rome. Then ſhould the prayers of the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ople which ſhould be borne a newe by the immortall ſeed of the word, be as the ſound of many Orators, for the preſeruation of her maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties perſon, the honourable counſell, the inferiour magiſtrates, and the peace of the whole land. Then, when the Lord his way ſhall be knowen vpon this earth, and his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing health among all this people, then ſhall our land bring foorth her encreaſe, &amp; God euen our owne God ſhall giue vs his bleſſing. Then ſhall it be knowen that the Miniſters of the Worde, are the chariots and horſemen of Iſrael. Moſt humbly ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we pray, and beſeeche our moſt grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soueraigne, and you the right honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Counſellers and the Nobility of this Land, you reuerend Fathers of the Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, you woorthy Iudges of the Lawe, and alſo you right Worſhipfull Knightes and Burgeſſes of the Lower Houſe, not to ſhrinck away and waſh your handes of this worke, but to raiſe vp your ſelues, and as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one hath receiued from Ieſus Chriſte
<pb facs="tcp:11944:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>greater wiſedome, authority, and magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity then another, ſo to ſtriue and contend one with another, to ſtrengthen the army of Chriſt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> place him in the royall ſeate of his king<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me. Which thing performed, as it woulde bee a glorious example for all Chriſtendome to imitate, and a day of ioy and ſolemnity, more excellent then that day which the Iewes helde for their deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from the conſpiracy of HAMMON, not onely in this preſent age, but alſo in all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities to come: ſo would it bee the dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt day to the kingdom of the diuell and Antichriſt, that euer was knowen in this land. Which our moſt mercifull father of his infinite mercy in Chriſt bring to paſſe: To whoſe bleſſing, and direction of his holy ſpirite, in all your affaires, and conſultations, wee commend you, with vnfained prayers this tyme and euer. Amen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11944:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:11944:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
